Guide to the Montana Legislature (43rd: 1973) records 1973-1974
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Legislature (43rd: 1973) records
1973-1974
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 43
Montana. Legislature.
17 linear feet of shelf space
Collection contains records (1973-1974) of the Montana 43rd Legislature including minutes of the House Special Committee on Gambling, Wild River Bill (HB 133), and Scenic Rivers; Senate Special Committee on Gambling, Apportionment, and Executive Reorganization; minutes of the Senate Democratic Caucus; minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees; House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, joint resolutions and memorials; and miscellany of the first and special sessions, interim session, and second regular session.
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 43rd Montana Legislature met from January 1st to March 10th, 1973, a Special Session held March 12th through 24th, 1973, and a Second Regular Session held January 7th through March 16th, 1974. The leaders of the Senate in 1973 were Bill Christiansen (D-President), Corine Thiessen (D-President Pro Tempore), Neil Lynch (D-Majority Leader), and Jim Moore (R-Minority Leader), and in 1974 W. Gordon McOmber (D-President), P.J. Keenan (D-President Pro Tempore), Neil Lynch (D-Majority Leader), and Jim Moore (R-Minority Leader). The leaders of the House in 1973 were Harold Gerke (D-Speaker), Walter Laas (D-Speaker Pro Tempore), Larry Fasbender (D-Majority Leader), and Oscar Kvaalen (R-Minority Leader), and in 1974 Harold Gerke (D-Speaker), (Speaker Pro Tempore – Vacant), Larry Fasbender (D-Majority Leader), and Oscar Kvaalen (R-Minority Leader).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
Collection includes minutes of the House Special Committee on Gambling, Wild River Bill (HB 133), and Scenic Rivers; Senate Special Committee on Gambling, Apportionment, and Executive Reorganization; minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees; bills and resolutions; journals and status reports of the first and special sessions, interim session, and second regular session. The collection also contains miscellany material including a sponsor list and the Senate Democratic Caucus minutes (re SB 665 [Circuit Breaker] property tax relief bill; SB 264 regarding homestead exemption; SB 266 and SB 248 regarding personal property tax relief; SJR 45 limiting the rate of taxation of real and personal property; SB 27 regarding codification and general revision of the laws relating to the Department of Labor and Industry; HB 699 regarding new limit for general fund budget increases on operation and maintenance of a public school; SB 532 regarding appropriations to Warm Springs; HB 147 requiring that the Department of Revenue be informed of sale price of all properties with the exception of agricultural land; HB 632 requiring an economic impact statement for certain proposed legislation; SB 226 and HB 221 to be combined as a tax package to replace the "Circuit Breaker" bill; HB 305 ["Veteran's Bonus Bill"] to provide $2,500,000 for Montana's Vietnam veterans; SB 696 to create a coal tax account in the trust and legacy fund; SB 614 regarding financing the vocational technology school in Missoula; SB 266 to exempt household goods and personal property from taxation; HB 166, 509, and 517 regarding coal taxation; disallowing appropriations out of the general fund for the Labor Relations Board and thus keeping to the long-range building program; HB 221 to raise income tax exemption; and SB 696 regarding coal taxation).
The collection is organized into the three subgroups, Regular and Special Sessions, Interim Session and Second Regular Session.
The subgroup Regular and Special Sessions is organized into four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany. The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into one subseries, Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically). The series House of Representatives is organized into nine subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Special Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), House Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Status Sheets of House Bills (arranged chronologically), House Journals (arranged chronologically), Subject Index to House Bills (arranged chronologically), and House Memorial Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number). The series Senate is organized into ten subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Select Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Confirmation Resolutions (arranged chronologically), Status Sheets of Senate Bills (arranged chronologically), Senate Journals (arranged chronologically), Subject Index to Senate Bills (arranged chronologically), and Senate Memorial Resolutions (arranged chronologically).
The subgroup Interim Session is organized into these three series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, and Senate. The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into one subseries, Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically). The series House of Representatives is organized into two subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically) and House Special Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically). The series Senate is organized into one subseries, Senate Select Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically).
The subgroup Second Regular Session is organized into four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany. The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into one subseries, Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically). The series House of Representatives is organized into eight subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Special Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), House Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), House Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Status Sheets of House Bills (arranged chronologically), House Journals (arranged chronologically), and Subject Index to House Bills (arranged chronologically). The series Senate is organized into eight subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Select Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically by committee name and thereunder chronologically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically by bill number), Status Sheets of Senate Bills (arranged chronologically), Senate Journals (arranged chronologically), and Subject Index to Senate Bills (arranged chronologically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Gambling--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Committees--Montana.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Regular and Special Sessions
  - House and Senate Joint Committees
    - Joint Committee Minutes
      - Appropriations: State Agencies (also includes Free Conference Committee on Claims and Finance), 1973 January 9 - March 20 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
      - Appropriations: University Subcommittee, 1973 January 9 - March 7 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
      - Long-Range Building, 1973 February 19 - March 14 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - House of Representatives
    - House Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, Livestock, and Irrigation, 1973 January 10 - March 17 (Box-folder 1 / 4-6)
      - Business and Industry, 1973 January 5 - March 21 (Box-folder 1 / 7-11)
      - Constitution, Elections, and Federal Relations, 1973 January 5 - March 13 (Box-folder 1 / 12-13)
      - Education, 1973 January 6 - March 21 (Box-folder 1 / 14-18)
      - Finance and Claims, 1973 January 2 - March 23 (Box-folder 1 / 19-20)
      - Fish and Game, 1973 January 8 - February 12 (Box-folder 1 / 21-22)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1973 January 9 - February 12 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1973 February 22 - March 21 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
      - Judiciary, 1973 January 4 - March 19 (Box-folder 2 / 2-7)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1973 January 17 - March 17 (Box-folder 2 / 8-10)
      - Local Government, 1973 January 8 - March 20 (Box-folder 2 / 11-13)
      - Natural Resources, 1973 January 4 - March 16 (Box-folder 2 / 14-19)
      - Public Health, Welfare, and Safety, 1973 January 4 - February 10 (Box-folder 2 / 20-22)
      - Public Health, Welfare and Safety, 1973 February 12 - March 15 (Box-folder 3 / 1-2)
      - State Administration, 1973 January 4 - March 22 (Box-folder 3 / 3-5)
      - Taxation, 1973 January 4 - March 20 (Box-folder 3 / 6-8)
    - House Special Committee Minutes
      - Select Committee on Gambling, 1973 February 26 - March 16 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
      - Select Committee on Wild Rivers Bill (HB 133), 1973 March 2-24 (Box-folder 3 / 10)
    - House Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-100, 1973 (Box-folder 3 / 11-17)
      - Bill nos. 101-420, 1973 (Box-folder 4 / 1-16)
      - Bill nos. 421-630, 1973 (Box-folder 5 / 1-13)
    - House Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 2-43, 1973 (Box-folder 5 / 14)
    - House Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-37, 1973 (Box-folder 5 / 15)
    - Status Sheets of House Bills
      - 1st-60th Legislative Days, 1973 January 1 - March 10 (Box-folder 6 / 1-3)
      - 1st-11th Legislative Days [Special Session], 1973 March 12-23 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - House Journals
      - 1st-60th Legislative Days, 1973 January 1 - March 10 (Box-folder 6 / 5-6)
      - 1st-12th Legislative Days, 1973 March 12-24 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
    - Subject Index to House Bills
      - Subject Index, 1973 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
    - House Memorial Resolutions
      - Memorial Resolutions, 1973 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
  - Senate
    - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, Livestock, and Irrigation, 1973 January 10 - March 7 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
      - Business and Industry, 1973 January 12 - March 20 (Box-folder 6 / 11)
      - Constitution, Elections, and Federal Relations, 1973 January 3 - March 19 (Box-folder 6 / 12)
      - Education, 1973 January 4 - March 20 (Box-folder 6 / 13-15)
      - Executive Reorganization, 1973 January 12 - March 22 (Box-folder 7 / 1)
      - Finance and Claims, 1973 January 1 - March 21 (Box-folder 7 / 2)
      - Fish and Game, 1973 January 9 - March 23 (Box-folder 7 / 3-4)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1973 January 4 - March 6 (Box-folder 7 / 5-6)
      - Judiciary, 1973 January 2 - March 8 (Box-folder 7 / 7-10)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1973 January 10 - March 5 (Box-folder 7 / 11)
      - Legislative Administration, 1972 December 27 - 1973 March 15 (Box-folder 7 / 12)
      - Local Government, 1973 January 9 - March 19 (Box-folder 7 / 13-14)
      - Natural Resources, 1973 January 5 - March 20 (Box-folder 7 / 15-18)
      - Public Health, Welfare, and Safety, 1973 January 10 - March 17 (Box-folder 7 / 19)
      - State Administration, 1973 January 5 - February 10 (Box-folder 7 / 20-22)
      - Taxation, 1973 January 9 - March 16 (Box-folder 8 / 1-3)
    - Senate Select Committee Minutes
      - Select Committee on Gambling, 1973 May 12 - December 3 (Box-folder 8 / 4)
    - Senate Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-212, 1973 (Box-folder 8 / 5-18)
      - Bill nos. 213-468, 1973 (Box-folder 9 / 1-13)
    - Senate Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-45, 47-85, 1973 (Box-folder 9 / 14)
    - Senate Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-40, 1973 (Box-folder 9 / 15-16)
      - Bill nos. 41-71, 1973 (Box-folder 10 / 1)
    - Senate Confirmation Resolutions
      - Confirmation Resolutions, 1973 (Box-folder 10 / 2)
    - Status Sheets of Senate Bills
      - 1st-60th Legislative Days, 1973 January 1 - March 10 (Box-folder 10 / 3-5)
      - 1st-11th Legislative Days [Special Session], 1973 March 12-23 (Box-folder 10 / 6)
    - Senate Journals
      - 1st-41st Legislative Days, 1973 January 1 - March 10 (Box-folder 10 / 7-8)
      - 1st-12th Legislative Days [Special Session], 1973 March 12-24 (Box-folder 10 / 9)
    - Subject Index to Senate Bills
      - [see subject index to Subject Index to House Bills]
    - Senate Memorial Resolutions
      - Memorial resolutions, 1973 (Box-folder 10 / 10)
  - Miscellany
    - Lobbyists registered with Secretary of State, weekly report no. 1, 1973 January 1 (Box-folder 10 / 11)
- Interim Session
  - House and Senate Joint Committees
    - Joint Committee Minutes
      - Constitutions, Elections, and Federal Relations, 1973 March 24 - November 2 (Box-folder 10 / 12)
      - Education, 1973 March 22 - November 10 (Box-folder 10 / 13)
      - Finance and Claims, 1973 May 7 - November 12 (Box-folder 10 / 14)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1973 May 7 - December 4 (Box-folder 10 / 15)
      - Judiciary Subcommittee on the Uniform Probate Code, 1973 March 22 - November 16 (Box-folder 10 / 16)
      - Judiciary Subcommittee on No-Fault Insurance, 1973 May 11 - November 16 (Box-folder 10 / 17)
      - Priorities and Rules, 1973 June 1 - October 5 (Box-folder 10 / 18)
      - Public Health, 1973 March 23 - October 16 (Box-folder 10 / 19)
      - State Administration, 1973 March 23 - December 4 (Box-folder 10 / 20)
      - Taxation, 1973 March 22 - October 26 (Box-folder 10 / 21)
  - House of Representatives
    - House Standing Committee Minutes
      - Legislative Administration, 1973 November 26 (Box-folder 10 / 22)
    - House Special Committee Minutes
      - Select Committee on Wild Rivers, 1973 October 12 - December 18 (Box-folder 10 / 23)
  - Senate
    - Senate Select Committee Minutes
      - Select Committee on Gambling, 1973 May 12 - December 3 (Box-folder 10 / 24)
- Second Regular Session
  - House and Senate Joint Committees
    - Joint Committee Minutes
      - Appropriations: Finance and Claims Subcommittee, 1974 February 13 - March 9 (Box-folder 10 / 25)
      - Appropriations: University Subcommittee, 1974 February 26 - March 6 (Box-folder 10 / 26)
      - Long-Range Building, 1974 February 4-18 (Box-folder 11 / 1)
  - House of Representatives
    - House Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, Livestock, and Irrigation, 1974 January 14 - March 12 (Box-folder 11 / 2-4)
      - Business and Industry, 1974 January 14 - March 6 (Box-folder 11 / 5-8)
      - Constitution, Elections, and Federal Relations (includes Joint Committee on Apportionment), 1974 January 14 - March 8 (Box-folder 11 / 9)
      - Education, 1974 January 10 - March 14 (Box-folder 11 / 10-12)
      - Finance and Claims, 1974 January 10 - March 15 (Box-folder 11 / 13)
      - Fish and Game, 1974 January 14 - March 6 (Box-folder 11 / 14-15)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1974 January 15 - March 14 (Box-folder 11 / 16-17)
      - Judiciary, 1974 January 9 - February 26 (Box-folder 11 / 18-22)
      - Judiciary, 1974 February 27 - March 14 (Box-folder 12 / 1)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1974 January 11 - March 13 (Box-folder 12 / 2-4)
      - Legislative Administration, 1973 November 26 - 1974 March 5 (Box-folder 12 / 5)
      - Local Government, 1974 January 11 - March 1 (Box-folder 12 / 6)
      - Natural Resources, 1974 January 15 - March 12 (Box-folder 12 / 7-10)
      - Public Health, Welfare, and Safety, 1974 January 10 - March 5 (Box-folder 12 / 11-13)
      - Rules, 1974 January 8 - March 15 (Box-folder 12 / 14)
      - State Administration, 1974 January 17 (Box-folder 12 / 15)
      - Taxation, 1974 January 9 - March 18 (Box-folder 12 / 16-18)
    - House Special Committee Minutes
      - Select Committee on Wild Rivers, 1974 January 7-9 (Box-folder 12 / 19)
      - Select Committee on Scenic Rivers, 1974 February 6 (Box-folder 12 / 20)
    - House Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-660, 1974 (Box-folder 13 / 1-24)
      - Bill nos. 661-1034, 1974 (Box-folder 14 / 1-17)
      - Bill nos. 1035-1133, 1974 (Box-folder 15 / 1-3)
    - House Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 3, 6-11, 14-15, 18, 21-23, 33-34, 38, 40, 1974 (Box-folder 15 / 4)
      - Bill nos. 44-92, 1974 (Box-folder 15 / 5)
    - House Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-82, 1974 (Box-folder 15 / 6-7)
    - Status Sheets of House Bills
      - 1st-59th Legislative Days, 1974 January 7 - March 15 (Box-folder 15 / 8-13)
    - House Journals
      - 1st-58th Legislative Days, 1974 January 7 - March 14 (Box-folder 15 / 14-15)
    - Subject Index to House Bills
      - Subject Index, 1974 (Box-folder 15 / 16)
  - Senate
    - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
      - Agriculture, Livestock, and Irrigation, 1974 January 14 - March 11 (Box-folder 15 / 17)
      - Business and Industry, 1974 January 11 - March 6 (Box-folder 16 / 1-2)
      - Constitution, Elections, and Federal Relations, 1973 March 24 - November 2 ,1974 January 11 - March 6 (Box-folder 16 / 3)
      - Education, 1973 March 22 - 1974 March 7 (Box-folder 16 / 4-6)
      - Finance and Claims, 1974 January 9 - March 16 (Box-folder 16 / 7-8)
      - Finance and Claims: exhibits, 1974 January-March (Box-folder 16 / 9)
      - Fish and Game, 1974 January 9 - March 7 (Box-folder 16 / 10)
      - Highways and Transportation, 1973 May 7 - December 3, 1974 January 10 - March 8 (Box-folder 16 / 11-12)
      - Judiciary, 1974 January 9 - March 14 (Box-folder 16 / 13-15)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1974 January 16 - February 4 (Box-folder 16 / 16)
      - Labor and Employment Relations, 1974 February 6 - March 9 (Box-folder 17 / 1)
      - Legislative Administration, 1974 January 8 - March 16 (Box-folder 17 / 2)
      - Local Government, 1974 January 10 - March 6 (Box-folder 17 / 3-4)
      - Local Government: exhibits, 1974 January-March (Box-folder 17 / 5)
      - Natural Resources, 1973 October 12 - December 18, 1974 January 14 - March 14 (Box-folder 17 / 6-7)
      - Public Health, Welfare, and Safety, 1973 March 23 - October 16, 1973 January 10 - March 13 (Box-folder 17 / 8-10)
      - Rules (includes Joint Rules), 1974 January 7 - March 9 (Box-folder 17 / 11)
      - State Administration, 1974 January 9 - March 13 (Box-folder 17 / 12-15)
      - Taxation, 1973 May 18 - December 4, 1974 January 12 - March 16 (Box-folder 17 / 16-17)
    - Senate Select Committee Minutes
      - Select Committee on Apportionment, 1974 January 15 - March 7 (Box-folder 17 / 18)
      - Select Committee on Executive Reorganization, 1974 January 14 - March 6 (Box-folder 17 / 19)
      - Select Committee on Gambling, 1974 January 15 - February 5 (Box-folder 17 / 20)
    - Senate Bills
      - Bill nos. 1-691 (includes senate debate regarding adoption of a new state flag, S.B. 613), 1974 (Box-folder 18 / 1-23)
      - Bill nos. 692-748, 1974 (Box-folder 19 / 1-3)
    - Senate Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-4, 6, 8-27, 32, 36, 1974 (Box-folder 19 / 4)
      - Bill nos. 38-52, 54-85, 1974 (Box-folder 19 / 5)
    - Senate Joint Resolutions
      - Bill nos. 1-70, 1974 (Box-folder 19 / 6-7)
    - Status Sheets of Senate Bills
      - 1st-22nd Legislative Days, 1974 January 7-31 (Box-folder 19 / 8)
      - 23rd-59th Legislative Days, 1974 February 1 - March 15 (Box-folder 20 / 1-3)
    - Senate Journals
      - 2nd, 4th-58th Legislative Records, 1974 January 8 - March 14 (Box-folder 20 / 4-6)
    - Subject Index to Senate Bills
      - [see subject index in Subject Index to House Bills], 1974
  - Miscellany
    - Sponsor list, 1974 February 5 (Box-folder 20 / 7)
    - Senate Democratic Caucus minutes (re raising per diem; Governor's Foundation Fund; removing Highway Patrol from Attorney General's Office; re feasibility of creating a separate Motor Vehicle Department; acceptance of HB 428 for the school foundation program; HB 54 placing enforcement of "Consumer Protection Act" under the Attorney General's Office; HB 241 re transfer of the State Board of Hail Insurance from the Auditor's Office to the Department of Agriculture; and HB 294 re abolition of the Division of Workmen's Compensation and transfer of its functions to the Department of Labor and Industry), 1974 January 2 - March 10 (Box-folder 20 / 8)
    - Senate Democratic Caucus minutes (re SB 665 [Circuit Breaker] property tax relief bill; SB 264 regarding homestead exemption; SB 266 and SB 248 re personal property tax relief; SJR 45 limiting the rate of taxation of real and personal property; SB 27 regarding codification and general revision of the laws relating to the Department of Labor and Industry; HB 699 regarding new limit for general fund budget increases on operation and maintenance of a public school; SB 532 regarding appropriations to Warm Springs; HB 147 requiring that the Department of Revenue be informed of sale price of all properties with the exception of agricultural land; HB 632 requiring an economic impact statement for certain proposed legislation; SB 226 and HB 221 to be combined as a tax package to replace the "Circuit Breaker" bill; HB 305 ["Veteran's Bonus Bill"] to provide $2,500,000 for Montana's Vietnam veterans; SB 696 to create a coal tax account in the trust and legacy fund; SB 614 regarding financing the vocational technology school in Missoula; SB 266 to exempt household goods and personal property from taxation; HB 166, 509, and 517 regarding coal taxation; disallowing appropriations out of the general fund for the Labor Relations Board and thus keeping to the long-range building program; HB 221 to raise income tax exemption; and SB 696 regarding coal taxation), 1974 January 6 - April 17 (Box-folder 20 / 9)